A Guide to the Southside Garden Club Records, 1914-2009 Ms.2007.032
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Southside Garden Club Records
1914-2009
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Southside Garden Club (1928/1930-) (Blacksburg, Va.)
Blacksburg Women's Club (1914-1970) (Blacksburg, Va.)
Ms.2007.032
7.6 Cubic Feet 14 boxes
The Southside Garden Club started as a committee of the Blacksburg Women's Club. The Garden Club became its own separate organization in 1930 and the Southside Garden Club was formed in 1941. Materials in the collection include newspaper clippings, minutes and yearbooks from the Blacksburg Women's Club. Southside Garden Club materials include organization reports, minutes, pressbooks, yearbooks, and scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Southside Garden Club Records were donated to Special Collections in 2007. Additional scrapbooks were donated in 2011 and 2018.
Historical Information
The Southside Garden Club began as a committee under the governance of the Blacksburg Women's Club. In the 1920s, in order to generate more interest in the Women's Club a committee was formed known as the garden committee. The committee first met in February of 1928, and in March of 1930 the committee voted to withdrawal from the Women's Club and formed its own independent organization. From the very beginning the Garden Club was concerned with community involvement and civic interests including the beautification of Blacksburg. In the late 1930s, the Garden Club's membership had grown beyond the capacity that could be accommodated by meetings in women's homes, in order to solve this problem, the club voted to split into three groups, the Arboretum, Southside, and Town and Country.
The Southside Garden Club, so named because many members lived on the south side of town, was federated in 1941. The Southside Garden Club continued the tradition of community involvement. In 1952, the club voted in favor of having women on the town council and in 1963, succeeded in making Blacksburg a bird sanctuary. It has furnished flowers and plants for various public buildings such as school grounds, Historic Smithfield, and the public library. Members of the Southside Garden Club have also participated in many contests and won awards in categories such as Garden Therapy and Horticulture. The primary mission of the Garden Club has always been the beautification of the town and county, and that mission continues even into the present day.
Scope and Content
The Southside Garden Club collection contains materials from the Blacksburg Women's Club and the Southside Garden Club. The Women's Club was a precursor to the Garden Club and materials included in the collection are minutes, yearbooks, publications, and newspaper clippings.
The Southside Garden Club materials include the organization's records and history as well as minutes, yearbooks, awards, and scrapbooks. The bulk of the collection is scrapbooks which contain photographs of floral arrangements and Garden Club members, newspaper clippings, and yearbooks from each year.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series each of which is arranged in chronological order.
Series I: Blacksburg Women's Club Material, 1914-1957: this series contains newspaper clippings, minutes, yearbooks, and publications.
Series II: Southside Garden Club Material, 1947-2009: this series is broken up into three sub-series described below:
Sub-series A: Records and Minutes, 1947-2005, this series contains annual reports and minutes of the Garden Club. The series is separated into categories and arranged in chronological order.
Sub-series B: Garden Club Awards and Pressbooks, 1964-2001, this series contains press clippings regarding garden club activities and booklets related to the contests entered by Garden Club members.
Sub-series C: Garden Club Scrapbooks, 1962-2009, this series contains the scrapbooks of the Garden Club.
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Women -- History; Montgomery County (Va.); Blacksburg (Va.); Blacksburg Women's Club (1914-1970) (Blacksburg, Va.); Southside Garden Club (1928/1930-) (Blacksburg, Va.)
- Blacksburg Women's Club Materials, 1914-1957
  - Blacksburg Women's Club, 1914-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1939-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook - Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Presidential Speech, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Virginia Club Woman, April 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Southside Garden Club Material, 1947-2005
  - Records and Minutes, 1947-2005
    - Membership Procedures, c.1985-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annual Reports, 1954-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1989-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs, "Golden Memories and Parliamentary Hints" (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Minutes, 1947-2002
      - 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Yearbooks, 1954-2005
      - 1954-1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - 1974-1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - 1993-2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Garden Club Awards and Pressbooks, 1964-2001
    - Flower Shows, 1964-2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Pressbooks - Publicity Contest, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Horticulture Award, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Garden Therapy Award, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Conservation of Water Award, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Civic Project Award, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Horticulture Award, November 1988 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Garden Therapy Service Award, October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Garden Therapy Beautification and/or Education Award, October 1989 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Newspaper Clippings - Award S-6, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Birds Habitat Award, December 1991 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Garden Therapy Services Award, November 1993 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Garden Therapy Beautification and/or Education Award, November 1993 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Tree Award, November 1994 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Roadside Improvement Award, November 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Garden Therapy Beautification and/or Education Award, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - National Award - Holiday Show, December 1996 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Membership Award, November 2000 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Horticulture - Herb Award, November 2001 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Garden Club Scrapbooks, 1962-2009
    - Loose Scrapbook Items - Newspaper Clippings and Photographs (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Scrapbooks, 1962-2005
      - 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - 2001-2002 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - 2002-2003 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - 2003-2004 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - 2004-2005 (Box 13, Folder 2)